Finding Aid for Frank A. Picard papers, 1907-1963
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Frank A. Picard papers 1907-1963
Picard, Frank A., 1889-1963.
852250 Aa 2; Ac
Chairman of Michigan Liquor Control Commission, 1932-1934, candidate for the US Senate in 1934, president of Michigan Bar Association, and U.S. Judge of Eastern District of Michigan, 1939-1963. Correspondence and other papers relating to Michigan and national politics, his work on the Liquor Control Commission and the Michigan Bar Association; also campaign speeches and scrapbooks.
3 linear feet
11 oversize volumes
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. Ruth Picard (donor 4083 ) and came to the library in 1963.
The collection is open to research.
Frank A. Picard was born in Saginaw, Michigan on October 19, 1889. He graduated from the University of Michigan in 1912, then went into private practice. In addition to the law, Picard also served in government as chairman of the Michigan Liquor Control Commission (1932-1934). He resigned in 1934 when he became the candidate of the Democratic Party for the US Senate in 1934. Though defeated, he remained active in party affairs throughout his life. From 1937-1938, he served as chairman of the Michigan Unemployment Compensation Commission and where he co-authored the Michigan Unemployment Compensation Act. In 1939, he became US Judge Eastern District, Michigan. He served until his death in 1963.
Judge Picard was active in numerous legal and service organization. He also was a gifted speaker and author of unpublished dramatic scripts and plays. One of these was "The Trial of Jesus" which Picard dramatized from a lawyer's viewpoint. His work on the trial of Jesus was a topic that he thoroughly researched. The result was serialized in the Detroit News in 1950.
Judge Frank A. Picard died February 28, 1963.
The Frank A. Picard papers consist of correspondence and other papers relating to Michigan and national politics, his work on the Michigan Liquor Control Commission and the Michigan Bar Association; files of campaign speeches and scrapbooks; and scripts and related papers for plays he wrote. The collection has been arranged into the following series: Correspondence, speeches and other materials; Scripts and plays; Other writings and miscellaneous; and Scrapbooks.
Subjects:
Depressions--1929--Michigan.; Judges--Michigan.; Michigan State Bar Association.; Michigan. Liquor Control Commission.; Michigan--Politics and government--1929-1938.; Michigan--Politics and government--1939-1945.; Michigan--Politics and government--1946-1960.; Michigan--Politics and government--1961-1970.; Michigan--Politics and government--1837-1950.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-; Picard, Frank A., 1889-1963.; Saginaw (Mich.); United States. Congress--Elections, 1934.; United States--Politics and government--1933-1945.; United States--Politics and government--1929-1933.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Courtrooms.; Judges--Michigan.; Picard, Frank A., 1889-1963.
Contributors:
Brown, Prentiss M. (Prentiss Marsh), 1889-1973.; Brucker, Wilber Marion, 1894-1968.; Comstock, William Alfred, 1877-1949.; Dulles, John Foster, 1888-1959.; Fitzgerald, Frank Dwight, 1885-1939.; Jones, Edgar De Witt, 1876-1956.; Mooney, Edward, Archbishop, 1882-1958; Murphy, Frank, 1890-1949.; Osborn, Chase S. (Chase Salmon), b. 1860.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.; Ruthven, Alexander Grant, 1882-1971.; Summerfield, Arthur Ellsworth, 1899-1972.; Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972.; Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951.; Wilson, Charles Erwin, 1890-1961.
Genre Terms:
Cartoons.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Correspondence, speeches and other materials
  The Correspondence, speeches and other materials series includes materials relating to party politics in Michigan in the 1930s and 1940s, Picard's 1934 senatorial campaign, the New Deal in Michigan, and party disputes. Unfortunately, Judge Picard destroyed much of this personal correspondence prior to his death so this series is somewhat fragmentary. A list of significant correspondents in the collection accompanies this finding aid. Although this series contains speeches, the researcher should also consult the Miscellaneous series for additional undated speeches.
  - 1907-June 15, 1953, 27 folders (Box 1)
  - June 16, 1953-April 19, 1963, 22 folders (Box 2)
- Scripts and plays
  Much of the Scripts and plays series concerns his writings on the trial of Jesus and other religious topics.
  - "To Live Together", 4 folders (Box 2)
  - "Father Forgive Them", 6 folders (Box 3)
  - "The Trial of Jesus" from a lawyer's viewpoint, 6 folders (Box 3)
    (include papers regarding proposed radio dramatization of the play by NBC)
  - "The Watch at the Tomb" 1951 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 3)
- Other writings and miscellaneous
  - Book: Dear Marie being a description of an automobile tour of Europe, 1953 (Box 3)
  - Book: Dear Marie-Again being a description of an automobile tour of the British Isles, 1955 (Box 3)
  - Charge of the Court: U.S. vs. Saul Laurence Wellman (Box 3)
  - Pamphlet: "How the Communist Mind Works" (Box 3)
  - Notes, printed, and various (Box 3)
  - Riddles, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Speeches, speech cards and notes, undated, 3 folders (Box 3)
    (see also campaign speeches and other dated speeches in the Correspondence, speeches and other materials series)
  - Photographs (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous: includes photographs and cartoons (Folder AC)
- Scrapbooks
  (includes clippings, programs photographs, and memorabilia)
  - 1939-1942 (Volume 1)
  - March 1942-April 1944 (Volume 2)
  - April 1944-June 1946 (Volume 3)
  - 1947-1949 (Volume 4)
  - May 31, 1946-May 30, 1949 (Volume 5)
  - 1949-1951 (Volume 6)
  - "Trial of Jesus" serial, Detroit News, March to April, 1950 (Volume 7)
  - 1951-1953 (Volume 8)
  - 1953-1955 (Volume 9)
  - 1955-1958 (Volume 10)
  - October 30, 1958-April 10, 1961 (Volume 11)
    (include material from the 1934 senatorial campaign)
Selective Index to Correspondents
Brown, Prentiss Marsh, 1889-1973.
Feb. 2, 1839
Brucker, Wilber Marion, 1894-1968.
Feb. 11, 1939
Comstock, William Alfred, 1877-1949.
Aug. 24, 1934
Dulles, John Foster, 1888-1959.
Feb. 10, 1953, Feb. 20, 1953
Fitzgerald, Frank Dwight, 1885-1939.
Jan. 14, 1935
Jones, Edgar De Witt, 1876-1956.
Mar. 25, 1939
Mooney, Edward, Apb., 1882-
Jan. 21, 1946
Murphy, Frank, 1890-1949.
May 6, 2935, Mar. 21, 1940, Aug. 23, 1946
Osborn, Chase S., (Chase Salmon), b. 1860.
Feb. 13, 1939
Roosevelt, Franklin D., (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.
Nov. 1, 1944
Ruthven, Alexander Grant, 1882-
May 10, 1940
Summerfield, Arthur Ellsworth, 1899-1972.
July 13, 1944
Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972.
Aug. 3, 1951
Vandenberg, Arthur H., (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951.
Feb. 11, 1939
Wilson, Charles Erwin, 1890-1961.
Feb. 11, 1953